Naveen Ralph, co-founder and CEO of
Unconventional AI, which is an AI chip
startup.
>> Best known for building and [music]
selling two deep tech companies. Naveen
is kind of definitionally outlier
founder. When I came there, we had about
a $20 million business and it was, you
know, 7 or 800 [music] million when I
left.
>> I don't think you really understand
something until you can build it.
>> Just because something is tried does not
mean it's [music] wrong.
>> I'm the opposite of an AI goomer. I
think AI is the next evolution of
humanity. We need innovation on the
hardware substrate to actually build
true intelligence.
>> Please welcome Naveen Ralph.
[music]
Hey everyone, great to be here. Um, you
know, switching gears a little bit to AI
now, which you may have heard a little
bit about. Um, it's super exciting to be
at this conference specifically because
as was said in the uh intro, I'm the
opposite of a doomer. I think AI is one
of the most transformational
technologies that humanity's ever
created and will enable us to get to
that next level of evolution which I'm
here for and uh this is sort of the
anti-doomer conference. So, let's go.
[laughter]
Um, so before we get going, I'll tell
you a little bit about myself. Um, you
know, I'm it's kind of weird. I'm really
right where I wanted to be my whole
life. Uh this was me at about five or
six years old, something like that. We
had a computer very early on, so I'll
date myself, but uh this was in 1978. We
got a computer. This is probably in the
early 80s. Uh learned to program when I
was a little kid. I just thought it was
like a puzzle. Um you know, learned to I
became an electrical engineer. Um really
because I enjoyed sci-fi and always
wanted to think about how I could make a
intelligent machine. And uh you know
then after a career in uh building
computers I went back to school and got
a PhD in neuroscience and the idea was
like let's go back to that thing how do
we make computers intelligent and
fortunately the whole world kind of
moved in this direction. So you know as
a technologist it's sort of the dream
right now.
Um a little bit about me tech uh from a
company entrepreneurship standpoint like
I actually founded the first AI chip
company called Nirvana Systems. So um
this was in 2014 if anyone remembers
back then there was no AI or at least
not in the common vernacular and uh it
was really hard to actually convince
people that this is important much less
to build hardware around it. Now you
heard from Jensen up here like the
largest company in the world a hardware
company because of AI. So we were early
on um I think I sold the company way too
early uh to Intel but I uh I ran I
started and ran the AI group at Intel.
Um, after I was done with that in 2020,
I actually started thinking about the
next problem, which was how do we build
bigger models like the large language
models we talk about today. And it was
about how do I build the infrastructure
to build those models? And so we started
platformizing GPUs and enabling it to
scale and making that easy to use for
other people. And after chat GBT
happened in 20 2022, we were kind of the
best game in town for people to start
building their own models. So took off
really fast. We decided to actually join
forces with data bricks. um that was in
2023 and and uh actually that's a
quarter of the total revenue of of data
bricks today. So um a lot of fun doing
that whole thing with uh Alli and team
at data bricks. And now I want to tell
you about unconventional AI which is
rethinking the foundations of how a
computer works. So there we're going
back to first principles here to really
trying to build a new machine. Computers
have worked a certain way for a long
time. We want to rethink that for the
singular purpose of making something
very power efficient and the goal has
been within it was initially within 5
years to get to a 1000x power
efficiency. I've actually revised this
to three and a half years because things
have gone faster than we anticipated.
We've actually solved very deep
scientific problems quicker because of
AI interestingly enough. So just a
little bit how are we organized? Like
we're truly a toptobottom company. We
start with theorists. These are people
with like math PhDs and um you know
theoretical neuroscience that kind of
thing. They come up with you know
concepts that we think would effectively
give us more power efficiency from the
perspective of moving less information
around and we then translate that into
models and that do real things trained
on real data and evaluated against real
criteria. So it's kind of the rubber
hitting the road of these concepts. Then
eventually we have to actually build
something physical. So these are people
who architect a physical circuit um
actually design those circuits uh model
them and see if it actually works and we
try to connect this whole stack
together. Um then eventually we have to
build a system and and a board and all
that kind of stuff and build a product.
So is energy really a problem? Uh I'm
not sure how much everyone in this
audience has thought about this but
interestingly enough I'll give you some
some data points here. This is one
company. This is just Google. I'm using
Google because Google has actually
talked about this publicly. um per month
they cross 3.2 quadrillion tokens. It's
a crazy number. I never even I never
think in quadrillions but that's the
world we're in today. And if I just take
10 jewels per token of energy. This is a
actually on the lower end of uh of the
energy spectrum for models. But let's
just take that number and multiply it
out. This is 12 gawatt. The US puts
about 40 gawatts of energy into data
centers today. And we're about half of
the data center capacity of the world.
And so, you know, we're under a 100red
gawatts of of data center energy in the
world today. 12 gigawatts is going into
one company just for AI services. So,
you can imagine if models get bigger
that that energy goes up and if demand
grows, which it is, that energy goes up.
So, we're going to run out of energy
pretty fast in like 3 years or so is my
estimate. So, really just putting it
graphically, this is what we have. You
know, we have this huge market that's
growing exponentially. call it a
trillion dollar market in 2030. Maybe
it's bigger than that. And then we have
this kind of linearized energy at the
bottom. And so you've heard a lot about
this today. Uh but this gap is the
problem. And we want to solve that gap
with technology.
So um I don't know if people are aware
of this, but the way we think about data
centers has shifted over the last
several years. It used to be about floor
space. Can I get the floor space? Can I
get the rack space? Then it was about
networking equipment. Then it became
about GPUs. Today it's about energy.
First you think about energy. I get the
energy contract and then I have to
figure out how to fill it and and
basically create u u um uh
infrastructure out of out of GPUs and
things like this about 50% of the cost
of serving a token. So every time you
try something on chat GBT 50% of that
cost is energy. The rest of it is the
capex of the hardware and the floor
space and all that kind of stuff. So
today we sort of think about oops we
kind of think about it as I get I get a
a power contract I need to monetize
every watt and simply put our business
case is pretty easy we're going to
monetize that a thousandx better than
existing hardware.
So then the question becomes, okay,
great, that all makes sense, but can we
actually do it? How do we build a
better, more efficient computer? Well,
biology actually provides some proof for
us here. So the human brain, you may
have heard this, runs on about 20 watts
of energy. And what's even more
remarkable to me is actually animal
brain. So that red number is how many
neurons are in the brain. And if you
kind of scale it linearly down to like a
a monkeykey's brain, it runs on one
watt. To put that in perspective, the
cell phone in your pocket runs on about
one watt. And other animals like you
know um rats and bats and things like
this. They run on millowatts of energy.
So just something that's pretty
relatable to everyone is a squirrel. You
probably watched how accurate they can
be. They jump between branches and they
do it perfectly a thousand times out of
a thousand. Their brain runs on 8 mill
of energy. You could run over a 100
squirrel brains on your phone and it it
has very precise and accurate behavior.
So biology created something quite
incredible. In fact, it's the right kind
of physical substrate for intelligence.
So, this is a quote I love. I don't feel
like we truly understand something until
we can create it. We've gotten a lot
better creating intelligence systems.
However, they do it in a kind of
inefficient way. What kind of
inefficiency is there? Well, as I kind
of hinted at the beginning, most of the
energy in a computing system goes into
moving information around. Just to put
some numbers on it, the human cortex,
the squiggly part of your brain, the
outside of it, um, only moves about 16
billion bits per second. That's actually
kind of a small number if you think
about it because there's, you know, some
13 or 14 billion neurons in that cortex.
Um, a GPU or, you know, a high-end
computing system moves nearly 30
trillion bits in and out of memory per
second. That's outside the chip. Inside
the chip, it's probably, you know, 10
100x more than that. So we're moving a
lot more bits in these synthetic systems
than the brain does. And that's actually
what drives the energy demand. And you
know how do we get here? You know
computers have been around for hundreds
of years actually in some form. They
were mechanical. They became analog
around the turn of the century and they
became digital back in the 1930s 1940s.
So this the operation of that computer
in 1940 1945 is actually very similar to
how they operate today. There's not a
huge paradigm shift. actually have this
memory on the outside. You have some
kind of computing and you move bits back
and forth. That operation creates a
machine that just requires a lot of
movement but it's very fast. We built
computers to be fast. They were always
faster than the alternative. Uh
incidentally that computer in 1945 that
was built called Eniac was built to do
artillery trajectory calculation and it
was built to do it faster than the
alternative. The alternative were humans
who actually did the calculations. Now
the alternative typically is some other
computer. this this computer is twice
the speed of that computer. That's how
we sell computers, but it's doesn't
contemplate energy efficiency. And
that's what we're changing.
And you know, these have been trends
going on for a long time where the
number of transistors kept going up, but
we couldn't keep scaling the frequency.
We could couldn't keep scaling uh single
thread performance. And now we're
actually not scaling efficiency any
longer. Moore's law, if you may have
heard of this, it's like making
transistors smaller has largely ended.
So we're not seeing efficiency gains
just from making transistors smaller. So
we need to rethink the problem a bit. So
how do we do it? Well, a good intuition
is that we cut out the middleman. So
computers have been built up with these
abstractions. So I mentioned digital.
Digital means one and zero. That itself
is an abstraction of the physical world.
Like we don't actually have systems that
behave as one and zero. A transistor
actually has states in the middle. But
we engineer it to behave that way. And
that that's an abstraction. So we kept
building these abstractions up and
eventually we started creating neural
networks and learning machines on top of
it. Each one of these abstractions
actually is lossy. It means it's
inefficient. It it it doesn't
contemplate all the complexity
underneath it. That's why it's an
abstraction. So what we're doing is kind
of simplifying this in some sense. We
find an abstraction of the physics of
the semiconductor and connect that to
the neural network. If you think about
your brain for a moment has a bunch of
neurons in it, but there's no linear
algebra. There's no uh floatingoint
math. It's actually the physics of the
neurons give rise to intelligence. We
want to kind of mimic some of that uh
with a semiconductor.
And this is also not a new concept.
There's actually computation all
throughout nature. Uh birds in a flock.
You may have seen things like this where
you know a bird does a simple behavior.
It looks left, looks right, and figures
out where the next guy's going. And when
they do that, they actually create these
interesting flocking behaviors, this
emergent behavior. And we see that with
ant colonies. Ant colonies actually do
intelligent things just by very simple
rules. And uh this study is called
dynamical systems theory. It's basically
how I get these emergent properties from
very simple behaviors of individual
components. Our brain actually works
this way as well. So we're taking these
ideas and actually starting to build
circuits out of them. So let me give you
an example of such a such a system. So
everyone here probably knows what a
metronome is. just, you know, when
you're learning to play the piano or
something like that, it's just tick tock
tick- tock physical thing moving back
and forth. So, this is kind of cool. If
you put multiple ones of them on a rigid
plank and that plank can just roll back
and forth, you'll actually see them
start to synchronize. And that's just
due to the physics of the system. They
each push against the plank just a
little bit. And even if they're off by a
little bit from each other, they'll all
synchronize to exactly the same phase.
You can actually scale this up to
hundreds of of metronomes on a physical
system and they'll all synchronize. So
this is actually a form of a dynamical
system that goes through you know some
starting point of all these different
phases and always synchronizes. You can
imagine a slightly more complicated
version of this where maybe they don't
all synchronize. Maybe half of them are
synchronized with each other and other
half are synchronized uh in an opposite
pattern or something like this. But the
idea is that this is a physical system
that that kind of uh behaves the way it
does just by by the the inherent
interconnection of the system itself.
Uh so we asked the question can we
actually use such a system like like
that metronome system to do computation.
We want to connect that to generative AI
that's what we really care about. So we
released a model we called UNO which
actually demonstrated this. It's an
image generation model that's built on a
set of oscillators like that. And uh we
simulated it and made it open source so
people can play with it. But this was a
f the first demonstration that I can
actually scale something up, train it
and actually get useful output like
image generation.
And uh you know this is kind of some of
the analysis that we uh we we provided
in that uh in that write up. What you're
seeing here is um we call this state
space trajectory. It's basically how the
system evolves in time. You can imagine
if you characterize the state of the
system as all the phases of those
oscillators um and then look at how it
evolves through time and you basically
condition that on the output. You say I
want to generate an airplane or a car or
a bird. It'll actually go through
different state space trajectories. And
so that's what we're seeing here is just
an analysis of this. And these are
actual images that were generated by it.
Now it turns out we actually started to
build a lot of that fundamental science
up over the last couple of months. And
we found other things that enable this
to work even better. So this is a
concept of what we call sparsity.
Sparsity means that you know if I have
uh let's say I have a bunch of elements
all connect to each other like we have
on the left hand side there. So you know
if I have uh 10 elements I want to
connect them all to each other. I have
10 * 10 elements. So I have a 100
connections. That's okay. But if I have
a thousand now I have thousand* 1,000
which becomes a million. So this doesn't
scale very well. We call this n squared
scaling. So the more I add, it actually
becomes way more hard to scale, right?
So that's not great. So sparsity allows
us to actually say, well, can I throw
away some of those connections? If I
throw them away now, can I actually
rescue the behavior of the whole system?
And it turns out you can actually not
only throw away some of the connections,
but you can actually get better behavior
out of the whole system. It actually
becomes more trainable. Uh there's a lot
of theoretical reasons for this, but we
actually are able to do this in um in
not only simulated systems, but actually
real physical systems. So, it's one of
these rare things where you get
something that's more efficient, uh,
that's actually more scalable and even
gives you more performance. So, this is
kind of a holy grail. It's been it's
been a problem for a long time, but we
had to frame the problem the right way
to actually find this solution. And so,
this is actually the first time I'm
talking about this publicly. This is uh
I wanted to do it at this venue because
I think uh um it's a really big deal.
This is actually the first physical
dynamical computer ever built. Uh, we
did this in 5 months. This company
started [applause]
Thank you.
started in earnest in January. We didn't
even have a team, but we said we're
going to build this first physical
prototype and do it, you know, this
year. And actually, we taped out the
design, meaning we sent it to the fab uh
in June on June 1st. The chip is back in
our lab, and we actually have results
from it. So, these are the first ever
images generated from such a computer.
Now, great, cool. But does it do
anything useful uh beyond just um uh
images? you can actually do any kind of
a task like sequence modeling or or
language models. But the interesting
thing here is it's only five 500 or so
nano per image. So to put that in
perspective a a normal computer like a
GPU is on the order of millig. So nanog
is 10 theus 9th. It's really really
small. So it's many orders of magnitude
more efficient than a standard computer
and it's because it just doesn't move
information around. This is proof
positive this works. So this is
literally the first time we're talking
about it publicly. So um yeah, thank
you. [applause]
So what's cool here is this is really
the emergence of something new. So
computers have gone from CPUs to GPUs
going more and more parallel to compute
and memory which is even more parallel
and fine grain. Um but all of these are
what we call vonoyman architecture. They
have a memory and compute and we move
information back and forth. What we
built is what's called a dynamical
computer which actually has compute and
memory in one thing. We don't have a
memory interface. Each individual
computing element is a memory. So it's a
completely different way to look at the
problem.
And so we call this 4D computing where
we use the time dimension in the
dynamics and we actually use the
physical three dimensions of die
stacking putting things vertically as
well as in a in a planer form. So we
have three dimensions from from the
physical and we have one dimension in
time. So this is actually kind of a new
way of thinking about a computer and it
it really is proving to work uh for
efficiency sake. So now what are the
implications if we build something
that's a thousand times more power
efficient? I think this is actually
pretty cool. So intelligence per watt is
what we care about. Can we optimize this
and make it better over time? There is
actually a thermodynamic limit which you
can never exceed. And uh the mamillian
brains though animal brains are
somewhere within one or two orders of
magnitude of that. Today we're on the
far left of this graph and we're about
10 billion times away. That's 10 one
with 10 zeros after it uh from that
thermodynamic limit. We think in that
three and a half years we can hit the
the limits of 2D lithography. And the
the overarching goal of this company is
to beat biology. We want to make
something better and enable you know
compute everywhere including compute in
new robotic um forms uh and things like
this in the next uh decade or so.
I think what'll be interesting is that
we'll see the shift going from like big
big data centers with gigawatts to many
small data centers all over the place. I
think this is a good thing. It actually
makes things that are more
environmentally friendly, more local,
more adaptive.
And as I said, I think enabling the
ability to build billions of robots that
kind of dynamically assemble to solve
problems in our world is something
that's I think is actually really cool.
This is something that will enable us to
think about bigger problems and do even
more.
And you know, I talked about AI being a
trillion dollar market. Well, if we
disrupt it by a thousandx, it's there's
a there's a concept called Jieven's
paradox where when you drop the
underlying um cost of an asset, you
actually consume more more than the drop
of that asset. So, if you make something
half the price, you'll consume more than
2x. If you cons you make something
1,000th the price, you'll consume more
than 1/ 1,000th of it. And uh I think
this will create the largest market that
humanity's ever seen.
>> I mean that was extremely unexpected. I
got to say that was pretty amazing.
>> Let me let me start with actually
probably the thing that's on everybody's
mind which is
>> to the extent that this works Nav and
you probably saw Jensen earlier.
>> There just needs to be an entire
ecosystem of people that are beside you
and around you whether it's the fabs
packagers etc etc.
What does it take to get from this early
version
>> to something that sits in somebody's
hand or that people use and how do you
see that path in terms of time and
complexity? What does that look like?
>> Yeah, timewise we're within two years of
of getting it to a full product. I mean
>> and what is the product?
>> Yeah,
>> it's a VM that sits somewhere that you
guys manage and
>> effectively we're we're building a new
data center product for so it's a whole
rack. as a system, right?
>> And the idea is that basically we'll run
those um uh models on it. And so tokens
in, tokens out through a network cable,
but the inner guts are completely
different than an existing computer.
>> And do you expect that you'll have to
move to support the existing model
families and existing architectures? And
will this work in a world where, you
know, we've spent all of this time like,
okay, KV cache and let's all like this
all just so mechanically reductive based
on, as you said, these abstractions that
we've lived on, right? So how do you
expect the rest of us to kind of move
towards this? Because I mean I think you
see that efficiency curve. We'd all want
it. So how do we take advantage of it?
>> Yeah. So I think there's a there's a
sliding scale between you know how much
better something is and how much pain
you'll you'll take to move to it. And
you know I I basically took the the tack
of like let's make it really really
compelling to move. There is going to be
some work to port things over. We
actually don't port at the operations
layer, you port the model layer. So yes,
the existing models will work, but
there's a fair bit of compute required
to make that transition happen
>> and very basic elements like mapm does
it is that exist in your it doesn't
exist. It's
>> I mean you can you can characterize it
as map but it doesn't implement it as
maple. Okay,
>> it implements it as a sort of time
varying behavior. But each one of those
time steps you can analyze as basically
a matrix of the current state times a
transition matrix.
>> And when you're building a team like
this like who are these people? These
are biologists plus physicists plus what
are these people?
>> Yes. Um like it's sort of like theorists
that that come up with these uh uh like
dynamical systems theory has been around
for 100 years. Yeah.
>> So we got people from that world and
then we got people who actually build
chips and they don't talk to each other.
>> They don't talk to each other.
>> So we had to facilitate that. That's
actually one of the most challenging
things about this company is the span of
talents that we have is so big that
getting them to kind of all coordinate
and build one thing is actually pretty
hard. Well, and what is this like CUDA
like equivalent, if you will, just to
use a bad analogy, that allows these
people up here to talk to these people
down there.
>> Yeah. So, we actually have built a set
of libraries in Python. In Python,
>> it's it's Python. It's not CUDA, but
it's uh you know, it's it's a language
of sorts that allows you to kind of
express time varying elements that have
stoastic behavior.
>> I mean, it's incredibly impressive. It's
so ambitious. Thank you very much. It's
great to see you. Great to see you.
Amazing. [music]